The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
Assalam O Alaikum(السلام عليكم), to you all.
We mentioned that Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه), the last Jewish tribe remaining in Madina
did participated in the Battle of trench, alongside the Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and Ghatafaan(غطفان).
Now let's go back to a conversation that occurred between Huyaiye Ibn Akhtab(حيئ إبن اخطب) and Ka'ab Ibn Asad(كعب ابن اسد),
who's the head of Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
Huyaiye Ibn Akhtab(حيئ إبن اخطب) belongs to Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير) and we talked about their fate
that they were besieged and then, they left.
They went to Ash-Shaam(ألشام) and some of them went and settled in Khaybar(خيبر).
Huyaiye Ibn Akhtab(حيئ إبن اخطب) was one of those who stayed in Khaybar(خيبر).
And he was carrying on his fight against Rasool Allah ﷺ
and remember that Huyaiye Ibn Akhtab(حيئ إبن اخطب) was the one who,
was discussing with his brother Abu Yasir(ابوياسر) the day Rasool Allah ﷺ arrived in Madina.
And Abu Yasir(ابوياسر) was asking him, is this him?
Meaning is this the Prophet that we have the description of in our books?
Huyaiye(حيئ) said: Yes it's him.
Abu Yasir(ابوياسر) said: Are you sure it's him?
He said: Yes, I'm sure, it's him.
So, Abu Yasir(ابوياسر) said: So what are you going to do?
He said: I'm going to be his enemy and until the end of my life.
He knows that he's the Prophet of Allah and he still insists that he will be his enemy, until the end of his life,
and Huyaiye Ibn Akhtab(حيئ إبن اخطب) was true to his promise.
So, he goes to Ka'ab Ibn Asad(كعب ابن اسد) the head of Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
When Ka'ab Ibn Asad(كعب ابن اسد) sees him approaching.
He locks his gates, remember these Jews used to live in fortresses.
So, he locks the gates of his fortress.
So, Huyaiye Ibn Akhtab(حيئ إبن اخطب) knocks the door and says, "open for me, Damn you."
So Ka'ab(كعب) said: Damn you Huaiye(حيئ), You're an evil man and you'd bring misfortune.
I've made a pact with Muhammad(محمد) and I'm not going to break my agreement with him.
I've never found him to be anything but trustworthy and truthful.
Ka'ab(كعب) was telling Huaiye(حيئ) just leave.
We have a pact with Muhammadﷺ and we're going to stick to it.
Huaiye(حيئ) said: Damn you open, so that I could talk to you.
Ka'ab(كعب) said: I will not.
Then Huaiye(حيئ) insulted Ka'ab(كعب)
and said: I swear the reason why you're locking me out
is that you are scared that I would share your dinner with you.
So, this embarrassed Ka'ab(كعب), and he opened the door.
Huaiye(حيئ) came in and he said: I bring you glory of all time, and a sea of goodness.
Ka'ab(كعب) said: What are you talking about?
He said: I bring you Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) with their chieftains and their nobles,
whom I have left, encamped at the confluence of the streams at Roma(روما),
along with Ghatafaan(غطفان) with their chiefs and nobles,
whom I have positioned at them at Naema(نعمه), near Uhud(أحَد).
They have made a treaty that they will not leave until we completely destroy Muhammad(محمد) and those with him.
Ka'ab(كعب) responded back,
he said: What you bring me, I swear by Allah is shame forever and a cloud that has lost its rain.
So, it's thundering and lightning and there's nothing in it.
Damn you, Huaiye(حيئ), Leave me to maintain my pact with him.
I have never found Muhammad(محمد) to be anything but trustworthy and honest.
So, Ka'ab(كعب) was responding to what Huaiye(حيئ) said, I bring you glory of all time and a sea of goodness.
He said: You bring me nothing but dishonor, you bring me nothing but shame forever.
And this sea of goodness that you're talking about is nothing but the cloud that has lost its rain.
So, it's making noise thunders and there's lightning coming out of it, but there's no rain in it.
So it's just show.
Huaiye(حيئ) wouldn't take no for an answer.
He kept on badgering Ka'ab(كعب),
until he was able to convince him, to break his agreement with Muhammadﷺ.
That shows you the insistence of this Imam(امام) of evil, Huyaiye Ibn Akhtab(حيئ إبن اخطب).
Now, the Battle of the trench was over.
Rasool Allah ﷺ heads back home, and he takes off his armor, and he takes a bath.
Ayeshaرضي الله عنها said, in Al-Bukhari(البخاري).
When the prophet صلى الله عليه وسلم returned from the trench.
And he had put down his arms and taken a bath.
Jibreel(جبريل) came to him and said;
So you have put down your arms, we've not done so I swear by Allah.
Go forth to them.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Where to?
Jibreel(جبريل) said: Over there and it gestured towards Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ and  the Muslims suffered a lot during the siege of the trench.
They're exhausted, cold, hungry.
And now finally they can take some rest and Jibreel(جبريل) comes to Muhammadﷺ and says:
Put your armor back on, pick up your weapons and go and fight.
So, no rest.
Rasool Allah ﷺ felt that the matter was so urgent.
He told the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم;
لَا يُصَلِّيْ اَنَّ اَحَدَكُمُ الْعَصْرْ اِلَّا فِيْ بَنُوْقُرَيْظَهْ
Do not pray Asr(عصر) except at Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
The matter is urgent, you have to leave now.
So, the Sahabah(صحابه) left.
But sunset was approaching.
And they did not reach yet, to Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
So, they discussed the order of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
لَا يُصَلِّيْ اَنَّ اَحَدَكُمُ الْعَصْرْ اِلَّا فِيْ بَنُوْقُرَيْظَهْ
You shouldn't pray Asr(عصر) except at Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
Some of them said that we have to pray Asr(عصر) now because it's already sunset,
and what Rasool Allah ﷺ meant by that statement is that we should rush and hurry up.
The other said: No, we're gonna pray over there, just as Rasool Allah ﷺ said.
So both of them wanted to follow, what they understood to be, the meaning of the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
When they returned and they brought the matter up, to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he didn't reprimand any one of them, he didn't disapprove anyone.
And this shows you that disagreements in issues of Sharia(شريعة) do occur,
they occurred in the time of Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
And you don't have to have one party necessarily wrong.
See Rasool Allah ﷺ approved both of them,
because they did their best in understanding, what Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted,
and they did it with the best of intentions.
Rasool Allah ﷺ laid siege to Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَأَنْزَلَ الَّذِينَ ظَاهَرُوهُمْ مِنْ أَهْلِ الْكِتَابِ مِنْ صَيَاصِيهِمْ
وَقَذَفَ فِي قُلُوبِهِمُ الرُّعْبَ فَرِيقًا تَقْتُلُونَ وَتَأْسِرُونَ فَرِيقًاَ۝
وَأَوْرَثَكُمْ أَرْضَهُمْ وَدِيَارَهُمْ وَأَمْوَالَهُمْ وَأَرْضًا لَمْ تَطَئُوهَا
وَكَانَ اللَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرًاَ۝
"And He brought down those, who supported them among the People of the Scripture, from their fortresses
and He cast terror into their hearts.
So, that a party, you killed, and you took captive a party,
and He caused you to inherit their land and their homes and their properties
and a land which you have not trodden,
and ever is Allah, overall things competent.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in this Ayah(آية), which is Surat Ul Ahzaab(سورة الاحزاب) verse, 26 and 27,
that He has brought down the People of the Book from their fortresses, and He cast fear in their hearts.
So, Jibreel عليه السّلام was telling Muhammadﷺ, to go to Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
And, which Rasool Allah ﷺ did and we talked about how the Sahabah(صحابه) had an argument on,
whether they should pray before sunset, or whether they should pray at Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه),
and they split.
Some of them prayed, while some of them waited, until they got there and then they prayed
and when they told Rasool Allah ﷺ about it.
He did not braid any of the two opinions,
which is very important because it shows you that in issues of Fiqh(فقه), for example,
there is room for different interpretations
because we would have different understanding of the text
but the point here is that one should follow the opinion because they believe it to be the truth,
not because it's the more convenient, not because it's the easiest, not it's because it is the easy way out.
No, you do it because this is what you really believe that Allahعَزّوجَلّ wants from you, to do.
That's an important principle.
If one has Ikhlaas(اخلاص), in this regard,
and they choose the opinion based on what they believe is the best Allahعَزّوجَلّ will reward them.
So, they laid siege to Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه) and it lasted about 25 days.
One narration is 25 and anothers 27.
And as we mentioned Allahعَزّوجَلّ said;
وَقَذَفَ فِي قُلُوبِهِمُ الرُّعْبَ
He cast fear in their hearts and He cast terror in their hearts.
And this is a soldier of Allah that we see comes up again and again
it happened with Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير), it happened with Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ will cast fear in the hearts of the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, Ka'ab Ibn Asad(كعب ابن اسد) gathers his people and he says, I'll give you three options.
I'll give you three options.
He said: You are aware of the difficult position in which we find ourselves.
I'm offering you three possibilities to choose from.
The first one is to believe in this man, Muhammad(محمد), and to follow him.
By Allah we are now certain that he is a prophet, and the messenger sent by Allah.
He is indeed the one described in our own book.
If you do so, you spare your own lives and protect your children and families.
They objected to this and they said;
"We will never abandon the Old Testament and substitute anything else for it."
So, Ka'ab(كعب) said, Since you refused me this possibility,
I suggest to you that we kill our women and children
and go out to fight Muhammadﷺ and his followers.
If we do so, we can fight much harder.
Since we have no responsibility behind us.
We can fight him, until Allah rules between us.
If we are exterminated, then we will face death without any worry about our offspring.
If, on the other hand, we achieve victory,
we will soon find new women and have new children.
They said: What would be the purpose of our lives?
If we kill these poor women and children?
I mean, what would we live for then?
He said: "If you refuse this also,
the only thing, I can suggest to you is that since tonight is the Sabbath(السابت) night,
it may well be that Muhammad(محمد) and his followers may relax their watch,
thinking that we would not do anything serious on the Sabbath(السابت) night.
Let us then take him by surprise and fight them to the bitter end.
They said: "Do you want to spoil our Sabbath(السابت)
and violate it, in a way that has never been done before
except by those whom you know, and who received the punishment, you know?
And then one of them his name is Nabbash Bin Qais(نباش بن قيس) said;
How do you expect us to take them by surprise
when you can see that they are getting stronger every day
in the early days of the siege, they were in their positions during the day
and retreating at night.
Now we see them into maintaining the siege day and night.
The surprise element is not in our hands.
Ka'ab Ibn Asad(كعب ابن اسد) looked at him and said;
None of you has ever made a firm decision since he was born.
So, they were thinking about surrendering.
They send to Abu Lubabah(ابولبابة), one of the Sahabah(صحابه), and one of their allies in the time of Jahilliya(جاهلية)
and they seek his counsel, what do you think should we surrender or not?
Abu Lubabah(ابولبابة) goes to them and when they asked him the question.
Actually, they meet him.
They came out with their women and children and they were sobbing,
imagine Abu Lubabah(ابولبابة), coming in with all of these women crying and, their children are crying.
So, it was an emotional scene.
So when they ask Abu Lubabah(ابولبابة); What do you think Muhammad(محمد) will do, if we surrender.?
He pointed to his throat and made a gesture that means, that he will slaughter you.
As soon as he did that, he realized that he has betrayed Allah and His Messenger,
he shouldn't have said that he shouldn't have disclosed any information that he had.
So, he rushed back and tied himself to a pillar in the Masjid E Nabwi(مسجد النبوي).
And said: I'm not going to untie myself, until Allahعَزّوجَلّ accepts my repentance.
Abu Lubabah رضي الله عنه remains tied up, for six days in the Masjid(مسجد),
his wife would come up to him, for every salah(صلاة) and untie him.
And then after Salah(صلاة) is over, she would tie him again.
And this continued until one night Rasool Allah ﷺ was at the house of Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه), his wife,
the room of Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه) and he smiled.
So, she asked him, O Rasool Ullah, what is it?
He said: Allahعزوجل has accepted, the repentance of Abu Lubabah(ابو لبابة).
So Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه) said; Shouldn't I go and deliver the good news to him?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes if you want to.
So, she opens the door of her room, which was right across from the Masjid(مسجد)
and she delivers the news to Abu Lubabah رضي الله عنه
and the Sahabah(صحابه), they rushed towards Abu Lubabah(ابو لبابة), to untie him.
But he said: Do not do so, until Rasool Allah ﷺ comes and does that himself.
So, Abu Lubabah رضي الله عنه, was affected by the emotional scene that he saw in front of his eyes,
the sobbing of the women and children in front of his eyes.
So, when he was asked: What do you think our faith will be.?
His response was.
Gesturing with his finger at his neck, which means that he will slaughter you.
And he goes back to the Masjid E Nabwi(مسجد النبوي), and he was terrified.
He said: I have betrayed Allah and His messenger, he realized that
after he acted.
It was a sort of a spontaneous move.
And he only realized his mistake after it occurred, but he was fast to repent.
And he was so serious about what he has done.
He rushed back to the Masjid E Nabwi(مسجد النبوي) tied himself to one of the pillars
and said, I'm not going to untie myself, until Allahعَزّوجَلّ accepts my repentance,
which Allahعَزّوجَلّ did after six days,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ received news of that.
So Rasool Ullah smiled and he told Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه) about it.
So Ummo Salamah(ام سلمه) was the one, who conveyed the news to Abu Lubabah(ابولبابة).
The Sahabah(صحابه) rushed to untie him.
Abu Lubabah(ابولبابة) said: No.
Until Rasool Allah ﷺ comes and unties me, himself.
So when Rasool Allah ﷺ went to pray Salah Tul Fajr(صلاة الفجر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ untied, Abu Lubabah رضي الله عنه.
And by the way, there is a pillar in Al-Masjid E Nabwi(المسجد النبوي), right now that is named the pillar of Toba(توبة).
This was the pillar to which Abu Lubabah(ابو لبابة) tied himself to.
He stay there for six days.
He wouldn't be untied except by his wife, who would untie him before Salah(صلاة), he would pray,
and then she would tie him to it again.
Still Bannu Quraidha(بنو قريظه), even though they got a hint that this would be their fate, agreed to surrender.
But they agreed to surrender when they knew that
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) would be the one, who would rule in their case.
He would be the judge,
and Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) was their ally, in the time of Jahiliyyah(جاهلية).
So they said fine, well that's good,
if it's gonna be Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ), whom Rasool Allah ﷺ is going to give him complete authority
to rule among us then we will surrender.
So, they surrender and they were tied up
and Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) was given full authority to rule in their case.
Now, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) if you remember was injured,
he was injured during the siege of Battle of the trench.
He was shot by an arrow in his arm and Sa'ad(سعد) made a Dua(دعا), he made a Dua(دعا) then.
His Dua(دعا) was.?
He said: My Lord, if we are to fight Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) again, spare me now for that fight.
There are no people I like to fight for Your cause more than those, who have opposed Your messenger,
rejected him and forced him out, of his hometown.
If you have willed, that this encounter between us and them would be the last.
I pray to you, My Lord, to make this wound of mine, my way to martyrdom,
but do not let me die, until I see our affair with the Quraidha(قريظه) have a happy ending for Islam.
So, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) was bitter at what Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه) did,
when they betrayed Rasool Allah ﷺ, in the bleakest of moments.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said, bring him, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ).
Rasool Ullah had prepared for him a tent in Al-Masjid E Nabwi(مسجد النبوي)
and he was placed in that tent, so that he could be cared off,
and Rasool Ullah would come and visit him,
because he was injured and he was laying down.
Now his injury was getting better but he still had to be carried.
So, they were carrying him to bring him to the gathering place,
where Rasool Allah ﷺ was, and the Muslim, and the Jews.
Sa'ad رضي الله عنه while he was been carried by his people,
the Aos(الأوس) were telling him, be kind towards Quraidha(قريظه).
And they were giving him advice because in one narration,
the Aos(الأوس) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
Hand over Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه) to us,
as you have handed over to Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع) to our brothers Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).
And should you remember, when he talked about Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع)?
Their affair was handed over to Abdullah Bin Obaey(عبدالله بن أبي), that head of Nifaq(نفاق),
he was the head of Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).
So, Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع) were handed over to him,
and we know what happened, he set them free.
Now Al-Aos(الأوس) and Al-Khazraj(الخزرج), would compete in everything.
Now since Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع), had an authority to rule over, their allies in Jahilliya(جاهلية), Bannu Qainuqah(بنوقينقاع).
Now Al-Aos(الأوس) wants to have that same authority.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said, then I'll leave the matter to Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ).
And Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) was the head of Al-Aos(الأوس).
So, they agreed.
Now Al-Aos(الأوس) were coming to Sa'ad(سعد), advising him to be kind towards Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
Sa'ad(سعد) did not respond, he was silent.
They were talking to him talking, talking, talking all throughout.
In the end, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) said;
لقَدْ آنَ لِسَعْدٍ اَلَّا تَاخُذَه’ فِى اللهِ لَوْ مَة لَائِمْ
It is time for Sa'ad(سعد), to disregard any possible criticism in serving Allah.
As soon as he said this,
some of the men of Al-Aos(الأوس) went back delivering their condolences.
They said, He's going to kill them.
If these were his words, that means, they will be dead.
لَقَدْ آنَ لِسَعْدٍ اَلَّا تَاخُذَه’ فِى اللهِ لَوْ مَطَلَائِمْ
It is time for Sa'ad(سعد) to disregard all criticism in serving Allah,
meaning, I'm going to do with please Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
I'm not going to look into the politics of it,
I'm not going to look into the what the media is going to say about it,
I'm not gonna look at what my family will say about it, what my friends will say about it.
I'll do what is most pleasing to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So you know, even though he didn't spell it out, but pretty much they understood that it means death.
And this shows you that the understanding of the Sahabah(صحابه) was,
that these people have committed the crime sufficient enough to be punished by death.
Sa'ad(سعد) was brought in.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قُوْمُوْ لِسَيٍّدِكُمْ
Stand up for your master.
Now we know that Rasool Allah ﷺ has discourage the Ummah(أمة) to stand up for its leaders.
However, this is an exception,
here Rasool Allah ﷺ, told them to stand up for Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ)
and by the way, we're going to talk in the end about, the virtues of Sa'ad(سعد).
Sa'ad(سعد) was a special Sahabi(صحابي).
So, they stand up in two lines to greet him while he's coming in.
And then they told Sa'ad(سعد), to give his ruling.
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh رضي الله عنه looked toward the Jews and said: Do you accept my ruling?
They said: Yes, we do.
Then he points towards the direction of the Muslims and he said;
Do you accept my ruling.?
Without staring at them because he doesn't want to look at Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he was so shy and embarrassed to ask Rasool Allah ﷺ, do accept my ruling.?
I mean, he was saying, who am I, to rule in the presence of Rasool Ullah.?
But since it was Rasool Ullah, who told him to do so.
He agreed, otherwise he wouldn't have done so.
So, out of respect for Rasool Allah ﷺ, he doesn't look towards him.
And he said and do you accept my ruling?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Yes, we do.
And now, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh رضي الله عنه will deliver, his ruling on the entire tribe of Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه)
it was a very important moment, very important ruling because it affects the fate of an entire tribe,
who has lived in Madina for hundreds of years.
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) said;
I hereby rule that all the men of the Quraidha(قريظه) are to be killed,
their properties to be divided and their women and children be enslaved.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَقَدْ حَكَمْتَ بِحُكْمِ الله مِنْ فَوْقِ سَبْعَ سَمَوَاتْ
You have ruled the same ruling of Allahعَزّوجَلّ from on top seven heavens.
This ruling of yours is the ruling of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
this is the ruling that would please Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
All of the men be executed,
the property divided,
and the woman and children enslaved
and this is the strictest ruling, acceptable in Islam,
sort of to say, it is the maximum sentence.
How would they separate between the men and the children?
Well, they didn't have any birth certificates in those days.
To tell how old a person is,
the way they would do it was by seeing if a person has grown hair, facial hair
or the hair that comes along with puberty.
In fact, in Abu Dawood(ابوداؤد), Attiya Al-Quradhi(عطية القرظي), said that they uncovered my pubic area.
And since I didn't grow any pubic hair, they set me free.
They spared my life, but he was enslaved.
So, this is how they separated between the young and the old.
How many of them were killed.
There's a variation in numbers.
It's between 400 and 900 hundred, some narrations say 400, some say 700, some say 800, some say 900.
These were the men of fighting age, who were executed.
Only one woman was executed.
And that is because she killed one of the Sahabahرضي الله عنهم by throwing a stone on top of him,
and this woman was sitting with Ayesha(عائشه)
and Ayesha(عائشه) has no idea about what this woman has done.
And this woman was laughing and joking.
And then Ayesha(عائشه) said and then suddenly, we heard her name announced.
So I told her, why is your name being called?
She said: They want to kill me.
She says, Why would they kill you?
Because she said, Because something a crime that I've committed.
Ayesha(عائشه) said, I will never forget how high spirited, she was,
even though she knew that she was facing death, I mean she was joking and laughing about it.
Probably it's this just the hysteria that comes in the last moments.
Maybe she felt there's nothing she could do about it.
All of them were killed except for some, who became Muslim.
Their lives were spared.
A few men here and there not many but some of them did become Muslim
and they were treated as part of the Ummah(أمة).
See, no racism in Islam, no Anti Semitism, you repent from your sins, you become one of the Ummah(أمة) that's it,
we completely forget about your past.
One of their woman, her name is Rayhana(ريحانه) was taken by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
She was a slave.
Rasool Allah ﷺ invited her to Islam, in the beginning she refused,
but eventually, it says that she did become Muslim.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ gave her the option.
He said: Do you want to remain as a slave or do you want to be freed and I will marry you.
She preferred remaining in the state of slavery.
So, she was a slave girl that was owned by Rasool Allah ﷺ, until he died.
One of the Sahabah(صحابه) appealed for one of the Jewish men
because this man has done him a favor in the time of Jahilliya(جاهلية).
So, he wanted to pay him, back for that.
And this man, this Sahabi(صحابي) was Thabit Bin Qais(ثابت بن قيس),
he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ to appeal for Az-Zubair Bin Bat'a(الزبير بن باطا).
Now  Az-Zubair Bin Bat'a(الزبير بن باطا) was an old man, who had become blind.
Thabit(ثابت) went to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and asked Rasool Allah ﷺ to spare the life of  Az-Zubair(الزبير )
and Rasool Allah ﷺ agreed,
but then Az-Zubair(الزبير ) told Thabit(ثابت),
what would an old man, who would have no son and no family do with his life.
So, Thabit(ثابت) went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and asked Rasool Ullah to free his wife and his children,
which Rasool Allah ﷺ did.
But then Az-Zubair (الزبير ) said;
What's to become a household in Hijaz(حجاز) that has no property?
How could they survive?
We're in the desert, how would I live without my property?
So, Thabit(ثابت) goes to Rasool Allah ﷺ and asks for the property of this man to be released,
which Rasool Allah ﷺ did.
So now, Az-Zubair(الزبير ) is free, his wife is free, his children are free and his property is back.
But then Az-Zubair(الزبير ) asked Thabit(ثابت), he said;
What became of Ka'ab Ibn Asad(كعب ابن اسد)
whose face was like a mirror that reflects the faces of the tribes, virgins.?
Thabit(ثابت) said: He has been killed.
Az-Zubair (الزبير ) said;
And what of our Vanguard, in the attack, and our protector in fight, Az-Zaal Bin Mua'al(الزال بن شموئل).
Thabit(ثابت) said: He has been killed.
So, what became of the two Council.
He said, They have dispersed and been killed.
Then Az-Zubair(الزبير) said, I asked you then, Thabit(ثابت),
by your obligation to me, to let me join my own people.
There is no good in life, for me now
that they have gone and I can't stand postponing joining my loved ones,
for so long as it would take, to fill an empty bucket, being born along by a camel.
Az-Zubair(الزبير) said: What's the purpose of living?
If my whole tribe has been exterminated,
so this man was so attached to his people, he didn't want to live without them.
And he was asking Thabit(ثابت) to pay back his favor to him, by making him join his loved ones.
So when, Az-Zubair(الزبير ) said that, that was his wish.
Thabit Bin Qais(ثابت بن قيس) went over time and cut off his head.
When the news of this reached to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), when he heard the statement of Az-Zubair(الزبير),
he said, I want to join my loved ones.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiq رضي الله عنه said: He'll meet them by Allah, in the fire of hell,
where he will dwell forever.
You want to join your people, Al-Yahood(اليهود), who died on Kuffr(كفر), fine you'll join them,
but will join them in hellfire.
Again, the men were killed and the property was divided.
Ibn Is'haaq(إبن اسحاق) said;
He narrates how the one, fifth was disposed of because this was a war.
So, four, fifth of the Ghanimah(غنيمة) was divided amongst the fighters.
And the remaining one, fifth was given to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And this is how, he used it.
Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق) said: The messenger of Allah dispatched, Saeed Bin Zaid(سعيد بن زيد)
with the captives taken from Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه) to Najd(نجد),
where he sold them in exchange for horses and weapons.
The Messenger of Allah had chosen for himself one of their women Rayhana(ريحانه),
he stayed intimate with her, until he died.
She still being at that time in his household,
the Messenger of Allah had suggested that she accept Islam but she had refused.
Eventually, she did accept Islam and this brought great pleasure to him.
He suggested releasing and marrying her but she chose to continue in slavery,
considering that easier for her.
She remained with him, until the Messenger of Allah died.
So, slavery in Islam.
I mean, Islam has changed many of the rules regarding this institution.
To the extent that here you have a person who chooses
to remain as a slave, rather than be freed.
Some lessons, from this Ghazwa(غزوة).
Why was the punishment so severe?
Why were 400 to 900 men slaughtered,
and the entire remaining population of women and children enslaved
and the whole wealth taken as booty, why.?
Why such a severe punishment.?
We can answer in one word, and that is,
"TREASON".
Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه) were the citizens of the Islamic State and they committed treason
and it's an accepted rule, that the punishment should be befitting of the crime.
The punishment should be proportionate, to the crime.
And since this crime is so great, they have committed treason against the Muslims.
They have committed treason against the Messenger of Allah.
Here we're dealing with the Messenger of Allah, we're dealing with Muhammadﷺ,
you lie to Muhammad(محمد),
you betray Muhammadﷺ,
you know, we're not dealing with particular head of state or a king.
We're dealing with Muhammadﷺ, he was the head of state, the messenger, the Seal of Prophets,
the most beloved of the creation of Allah to Allah
and they betray him, they lie to him, they conspire against him.
So, the punishment can be no less than what Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) chose.
And that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ was happy with it.
And he said that this was the rule of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, from above seven heavens.
Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) said: All that was due to their disbelief,
their breaking of pacts between themselves and the Messenger of Allah.
And they're allying themselves with the clans against him.
None of that did them any good,
and brought the Wrath of Allah and His Messenger down upon them,
a bad bargain for them in this world and the next.
So, they received the punishment that, they deserved.
Next lesson, Sa'ad(سعد) refused to be lenient in his ruling,
because he knew that leniency in such matters is weakness.
It's not a sign of mercy or compassion, it's a sign of weakness.
And in such situations, the only medicine is to be firm.
So, the perception that some Muslims have that
Muslims should be lenient with their enemies, so that we don't want to give Islam a bad image.
We want people to say that we are tolerant and peaceful.
We don't want them to say that Muslims are terrorists.
This is a sign of weakness and failure.
We can see today some of the Muslim leaders speaking soft words
But that only adds to their aggressiveness and the arrogance of the enemy.
So, sometimes the sword needs to be used,
and sometimes the word of wisdom needs to be used.
So, one needs to use the right instrument, the right time.
Sometimes the pen sometimes, it's the sword,
sometimes it's a Muo'ezza(موضة) of Qur'an and sometimes it is the Sultaan(سلطان).
The authority of the Islamic Khalifah(خليفه).
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) says;
اِنَّ الله يَزْعَ بِالْسُلْطَانْ مَالَا يَزْع بِالْقُرآنْ
Sometimes Allah can fulfill some of the objectives of the religion through the Sultan(سلطان) through the Muslim authority
that cannot be fulfilled through the Qur'an.
There are some lessons in the statement of Sa'ad(سعد).
The statement that we read, he said;
My Lord, if we are to fight Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) again, spare me now, for that fight.
There are no people I like to fight for Your cause
more than those who have opposed Your messenger,
rejected him and forced him out of his hometown.
Sa'ad(سعد), being the head of one of the tribes of Al-Ansaar(الانصار),
wanted to carry on fighting Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), if there is any fighting left,
we have given Rasool Allah ﷺ a pledge that we will defend him.
And since it was the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
who have driven him out of his home and brought him to Madina,
we're going to fight for the Messenger of Allah, until Allah defeats Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, he said, if there's any fighting left, I want to live and be there.
But then he said;
If You have willed, that this encounter between us would be the last.
I pray to You, my Lord to make this wound of mine my way to martyrdom.
So, here he is asking Allah to make him die.
If there's no fighting left with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
this shows us that Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) has no objective in living,
except to fight the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), to fight Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
He doesn't want to live to cultivate his land,
he doesn't want to live to marry some beautiful women,
he doesn't want to live to, just because of the sake of loving life,
like it is the case with most of mankind
their only attachment to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is their attachment to life,
they might have a miserable life but they still want to live it.
Sa'ad(سعد) wants to live for noble purpose to fight Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
There's no fighting left, then O Allah make me die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
And then he said;
And don't let me die until I see our affair with Quraidha(قريظه) have a happy ending with Islam.
These were his allies.
But now because his alliance is to Rasool Ullah,
he was asking Allah to not make him die, until he sees a happy ending to the affair of Muslims and Bannu Quraidha(بنو قريظه)
and Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), Allah made him be the person to rule among Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
If you want to see a happy ending, then you'll be the one to choose it.
Next lesson,
the Battle of Quraidha(قريظه) is a special Ghazwa(غزوة), for the following reasons.
Number one, it was commanded by Jibreel(جبريل),
Jibreel(جبريل) came to Muhammadﷺ said: Go and fight Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظة).
Number two, Jibreel(جبريل) accompanied the Muslims.
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) says in Al-Bukhari(البخاري),
It was as though I could see the dust rising in the streets of Bannu Ghanam(بنوغنم),
due to the marching of Jibreel(جبريل)'s troops
when Rasool Allah ﷺ set out against Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظة).
So, Jibreel عليه السّلام went to fight against these Yahood(يهود).
The next reason, why it's special,
the execution of Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظة) was a command from Allah,
delivered on the tongue of Sa'ad(سعد).
So, this was what Allahعَزّوجَلّ wanted, this was the ruling that pleased Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
even though it was a very strict, it was harsh, but this is what Allahعَزّوجَلّ wanted.
And this shows you that, this Ghazwa(غزوة) was a special Ghazwa(غزوة).
And this Ghazwa(غزوة) was a Ghazwa(غزوة), that drove out the last tribe of Yahood(يهود) in Madina.
Some virtues of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh رضي الله عنه, this Special Man, this Sahabi(صحابي).
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) was the head of Al-Aos(الأوس).
After the ruling was delivered on the Yahood(يهود) of Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظة),
the injury of Sa'ad(سعد) which was almost entirely healed.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), it again opened and it caused the death of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ).
So the Dua(دعا) of Sa'ad(سعد) was fulfilled.
First of all, there was no more fighting with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Number two, he died as a Shaheed(شهيد) because of his wound.
Number three, he saw a happy ending to the affair of Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قُوْمُوْ لِسَيٍّدِكُمْ
Stand up for your master.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ called him, master
and he's the only man, whom we know that Rasool Allah ﷺ told the Sahaba(صحابه) to stand up for,
that's one of his virtues.
Next, when Rasool Allah ﷺ heard the news of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) dying,
he rushed towards him, with the Sahabah(صحابه) and he told them, to come along with him
and he was walking so fast the shoes of the Sahabah(صحابه) were tearing,
and their garments were falling down.
So, they told Rasool Ullah about it, they complained about it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I want to go there.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اِنِّيْ اَخَافُ اَنْ تَسْبِقنَا اَلْمَلآئكَهْ فَتُغَسِّلُكَ مَا غَسَّلَتْ حَنْظَلَهْ
I'm afraid that the angels will reach there before us.
So, the angels were rushing to go towards Sa'ad(سعد).
That's another of his virtues.
Another virtue,
when he died, the mother of Sa'ad(سعد) was weeping.
She was mourning on her son,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Every mourner is exaggerating, except for the mother of Sa'ad(سعد).
You have a reason to cry, you have a reason to mourn, the death of Sa'ad(سعد)
because he was such a Muslim.
كُلُّ نَائحة تَكْذِبَ اِلَّا اُمُّ سَعْد
When they carried the Janazah(جنازة) of Sa'ad(سعد), it was so light,
so they went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they said it was so light,
it was as if, it was empty, his body wasn't there.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; And why shouldn't it be light
when angels that never came down to Duniyah(دنيا) came down
to participate, in carrying the Janazah(جنازة) of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ),
Angels who never came down to Duniyah(دنيا)
came down specially to participate in the funeral of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh رضي الله عنه,
and they were carrying his body alongside the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
This is such a great Sahabi(صحابي).
And the greatest, the greatest virtue of all,
a virtue that we didn't hear was attributed to any Sahabi(صحابي) other than him,
was the virtue that was mentioned by Rasool Allah ﷺ in Sahih Muslim(صحيح مسلم).
Rasool Ullah said;
اِهْتَز عَرْشُ الرَّحْمنِ لِمَوْتِ سَعْد اِبن معاذ
The throne of Allah shook Because of the death of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ).
The throne of Allah, the creator of the universe moved, it was shaking. Why?
Because of the death of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh رضي الله عنه.
This is how great Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) was.
And some of the scholars say that the reason why the throne of Allah shook
was, because of the commotion that was caused among the angels,
who are carrying the throne of Allah, when they knew that Sa'ad(سعد) died,
commotion sort of occurred and that caused the throne of Allah to shake, رضي الله عن, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh رضي الله عنه.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ never forgot about Sa'ad(سعد).
I mean, even after he died, he was still remember him.
One day Rasool Allah ﷺ received gifts.
He received some pieces of cloth
that the Sahabah(صحابه) never, never saw the likes of those piece of cloth,
probably they were cloth of silver, garments of silver.
So, the Sahabah(صحابه) were holding this cloth.
Every one of them wanted to touch it and they were testing it,
they wanted to touch this beautiful fabric, they were so impressed with it
and Rasool Allah ﷺ saw this crowd taking look at this piece of cloth.
So, he said;
اَتَعْجَبُوْنَ مِنْ لِيْنِيْ هَذَهْ
Are you amazed at how soft this cloth is?
They said; Yes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَمَا نَادِيْلُ سَعْدْ اِبْنِ مُعَاذْ فِي الْجَنَّةْ’ خَيْرٌ مِّنْهَا وَاَلْيَنْ
The handkerchiefs of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ) in Jannah(جنة) are softer and better than this cloth,
the handkerchief, not the garment.
The tissues, the handkerchiefs of Sa'ad(سعد) in Jannah(جنة), are better than this.
Now, with all of these virtues of Sa'ad(سعد), with the special status of Sa'ad(سعد),
when they were burying Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ),
when they lowered his body into the grave,
and when they were covering his body.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was standing right on top of the grave, and suddenly his face changed.
And then he said;  Subhan Allah(سبحان الله) three times.
Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), Subhan Allah(سبحان الله).
The Sahabah(صحابه) repeated the Subhan Allah(سبحان الله) after him.
It says that you could hear the voices in Al-Baqiyah(البقيه), in the cemetery,
they were saying Subhan Allah(سبحان الله).
And then the face of Rasool Ullah returned to usual.
And he said, Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر), Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر), Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر).
They asked Rasool Allah ﷺ, why did you say that?
Why did you make Tasbeeh(تسبيح) and then you make Takbeer(تكبير)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
تَضَايق عَلَى صَاحِبْكُمُ الْقَبْر، وَضُمَّ ضَمَّ
اِنَّ نَجَّا مِنْهَا اَحَدٌ لَا نَجَا هُوَّ ثُمَّ فُرِّجَ عَنْهَ
The grave squeezed the body of Sa'ad(سعد)
and if there was going to be anyone, who would be spared of that suffering of the squeezing of the grave,
it would have been Sa'ad(سعد).
And then the grave released, itself.
So the earth released itself,
the earth would squeeze in the body of a person, when he's buried.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was worried,
when he saw that and he said, Subhan Allah(سبحان الله) and his face changed,
he was feeling sorry for Sa'ad(سعد).
But then when the earth released the body of Sa'ad(سعد),
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر).
So, dear brothers and sisters, we ask Allah, to spare us from the punishment of the grave.
We asked Allahعَزّوجَلّ to make our time in the graves, times of blessing of Naimah(نعمة),
because the righteous servant of Allah will see his place in Jannah(جنة),
we ask Allah, to make us of those.
We ask Allah to spare us from the Fittan(فتن)
you know, we have the Sakaraat-Ul-Moat(سكرات الموت) and you have the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of Al-Qabr(القبر).
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to save us from all of those.
This was the great Sahabi رضي الله عنه, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاذ),
he was the head of Al-Aos(الأوس),
how old was he, when he died?
Thirty seven(37) years old.
Meaning that when Rasool Allah made Hijrah(هجرة) he was 30 years old.
He became Muslim before that.
So, here you have a young man giving his prime life to the service of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
until he died for the sake of Islam.
This is the meaning of Nusrah(نصرة),
giving Nusrah(نصرة) to the religion, giving support to the religion.
It's not that you stayed home, laid back, attend the Islamic conferences in the five star hotels,
go to your mosque, comfortable driving in an air conditioned car, in summer,
using the heater, when it's winter,
and then you think that you have done the best that you could do for the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
without suffering a bit, without spending a dime, without shedding a drop of blood.
That wasn't how the Ansaar(الانصار) did it.
That wasn't their understanding of religion.
They spared nothing, for the sake of serving Allahعَزّوجَلّ and His messenger Muhammadﷺ,
and that's why they deserved to be called Al-Ansaar(الانصار).
Dear brothers and sisters;
Rasool Allah ﷺ after the Battle of the trench said;
اَلْآنَ نَغْزُوهُمْ وَلاَ يَغْزُونَنَا
From now on, we will attack them and they will not attack us.
So, the Battle of a trench was a turning point, in the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
It represented the move from the stage of defensive Jihad(جهاد) to the stage of offensive Jihad(جهاد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: From now on, they will not attack us,
we will be the ones, who attack them.
So, we are done with the first stage of Madina
and that is the stage of Jihad-Ud-Daffah(جهاد الدفعه),
the defensive fighting Fee-sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله).
And the following stage is the stage of offensive Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
we ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to accept from us, our deeds.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to make us of those, who understand the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ and follow it.
We ask Allah, to make us of those who will give support, Nusrah(نصرة) to His religion.
This is our last session in the first part of Madina.
رَبَّنَا آتِنَا فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً وَقِنَا عَذَابَ النَّارِ۝
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
I ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to accept from us, what past from Ramadhan(رمضان)
and we ask Allah to help us, for what is remaining.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to reward us with Jannah(جنة) and to save us from Hellfire.
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته